Mss.B.B171
American Philosophical Society
Oliver Edwin Baker papers, 1913-1949
Mss.B.B171
American Philosophical Society
2.5 Linear feet
2.5 linear ft.
The material pertains chiefly to the 1913-1933 period of his career when he was working on the "Atlas of World Agriculture," and on the Pioneer Belts Projects. There is material relating to the Association of American Geographers, "Economic Geography," and the Institute of Pacific Relations.
Association of American Geographers.
Baker, O. E., (Oliver Edwin), 1883-1949
Bowman, Isaiah, 1878-1950
Buck, John Lossing, 1890-1975
Condliffe, J. B., (John Bell), 1891-1981
East, Edward M., (Edward Murray), 1879-1938
Ely, Richard Theodore, 1854-1943
Merk, Frederick, 1887-1977
Smith, J. Russell, (Joseph Russell), 1874-1966
Box 1-5
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by Alice Crew Baker, 1973; accessioned, 1974 (1974 1347ms).
Biographical/Historical note
Oliver Edwin Baker (1883-1949) was an agricultural geographer and population expert and an analyst for the U.S. Department of Agriculture. He was an authority on agricultural land utilization and advocate of “rurban” living, a combination of urban employment, suburban living, and part-time farming.
Baker was born in 1883 in Tifflin, Ohio, to Edwin Baker, a merchant, and his wife Martha Ranney Thomas. As a boy Baker was taught by his mother, a former school teacher, and then in public school. He graduated at age nineteen from Heidelberg College in Tifflin with a major in history and mathematics. The following year he received his master’s degree in philosophy and sociology from Heidelberg. He then enrolled at Columbia University, where he was granted a master’s in political science. He subsequently studied forestry at Yale (1907-1908) and agriculture at the University of Wisconsin (1908-1912). During his time at Wisconsin he co-authored an essay on the climate of Wisconsin and its effects on agriculture, and he spent his summers with the Wisconsin Soil Survey. In 1912 Baker joined the United States Department of Agriculture. Five years later he co-authored the Geography of the World’s Agriculture. The positive reception of this volume motivated Baker to produce an Atlas of American Agriculture, which was published in six parts between 1918 and 1936. Baker subsequently returned to the University of Wisconsin, where he earned a Ph.D. in economics in 1921 with a dissertation on land utilization. His research interests in the economics of agriculture stemmed in part from the influence of two of his professors at Wisconsin, Henry C. Taylor (1873-1969) and Richard T. Ely (1854-1943).
In 1922 Baker accepted Taylor’s invitation to join the Department of Agriculture’s new Bureau of Agricultural Economics. There he undertook a number of research projects, including many that involved the delineating and mapping of agricultural regions. His “Agricultural Regions of North America” was published in several parts between 1926 and 1933 in Economic Geography, for which he also served as associate editor for several years. He evidently often amazed his students by citing statistics on any of the 300 counties in the United States. Among his other publications during this period was an essay on agriculture in China that appeared in Foreign Affairs (1928). Baker was vice president of the Association of American Geographers in 1824 and president in 1932. During this period he was involved in the Association’s long-term program to investigate the “the margin of the cultivable earth,” so-called pioneer belts. In the late 1920s he also belonged to a National Research Council’s committee charged with the study of pioneer belts. From 1923 to 1927 Baker taught part-time in the newly established geography department at Clark University in Worcester, Massachusetts.
By the 1930s Baker became increasingly interested in questions related to population studies, including rural-urban migration, population quality, and living conditions on farms. Baker’s research in population problems stemmed from his interest in what he saw as the most valuable farm product, outstanding citizens. He encouraged and participated in several surveys of rural youth, and, based on his recognition that many rural people live in unsatisfactory conditions, he devoted much energy to improving their circumstances. For example, he attempted to the future of farming by studying past agricultural trends, offered specific suggestions designed to improve farming practices, and he tried to increase popular awareness of the contributions of farm families to the nation’s welfare. He essentially saw the nation as a complex of agricultural regions, and while some geographers regarded his agrarianism as reactionary, others recognized his contributions especially in the mapping of these regions. In 1937 the University of Göttingen awarded him an honorary degree.
Baker was deeply concerned about the declining U.S. birthrate, especially among urban people, which he predicted would have devastating consequences for the entire nation. He was a strong advocate of a “rurban” lifestyle that would combine urban employment with suburban living and part-time farming. This, he believed, would help preserve the rural values he so admired, including the “family ideal,” “the worth of the human soul, patriotism, the dignity of labor, the necessity of sacrifice, and the widespread distribution in the ownership of property,” as he explained in his essay “Some Implications of Population Trends to the Christian Church” (1942). Baker also believed that a “rurban” society would help improve land-use practices and increase the birthrate. He called for farm ownership over many generations, with one dwelling reserved for the older couple and one for the younger. Baker and his wife Alice Hargrave Crew, whom he married in 1925, practiced what he preached. The couple raised four children on a suburban property where they grew a garden and raised cows and chickens. Baker eventually bought a farm in Virginia with the intention of leaving it to his son.
In 1942 Baker joined the faculty of the University of Maryland. At that time, the university offered no courses in geography. Over the next seven years, Baker established what became one of the foremost geography departments in the country. He retired as chairman in 1949 in order to focus on his research, especially in connection to the Atlas of World Resources and the China Atlas. He died later that year in his home in College Park, Maryland.
Baker, Alice Crew; Institute of Pacific Relations.; Pioneer Belts Projects.; Agriculture -- Atlases.; Agriculture -- Research.; Economic geography.; Geographers.; Geography -- United States -- Societies, etc.
- Papers
  - Abbot, Grace
    Scope and Contents note
    General note
    See: See also:
  - Adams, James Truslow
  - Allred, C E
  - Alsberg, Carl L., 3.0 folders
  - Altorfer Brothers Company
  - American Consular Service
  - American Country Life Association
  - American Education Press, Inc.
  - American Society of Naturalists
    See also: Naturalists, in:
  - The American Sociological Society
  - Anderson, Thomas M
  - The Annalist
  - The Association of American Geographers
  - Baber, R E
  - Baker, Alice Crew
  - Baker, Oliver Edwin, miscellany
  - Baker, Sabra
  - Baltimore Feed & Grain Company
  - Bandig, H
  - Bengston, Nels A
  - Bensin, Basil M
  - Benson, O H
  - Benton and Bowles, Inc.
  - Beveridge, Sir William
  - Bishop, W Howard
  - Blackwell, C P
  - Blakeman, Edward W
  - Bonavia, William J
  - Booth, J F
  - Bowman, Isaiah, 1878-1950; 4.0 folders
    See also: Frederick Merk; Social Science research Council. Committee on problems
  - Bowman, Paul H
  - Brenau College
  - Brazier, William A.
  - Brenau College
  - Bressman, E N
  - Brigham, Albert Perry
  - Brigham Young University
  - The Brookings Institution
  - Brownell, Baker
  - Brundage, A J
  - Brunner, Edward deS
  - Bryant, T R
  - Bucholtz, A F
  - Buck, J. Lossing, 2.0 folders
  - Burlison, W L
  - Butler, Nicholas Murray
    See also: Proskauer, Joseph M., in:
  - Calvert, Robert
  - Campbell, Editha C
  - Campbell, R M
  - Canadian National Research Council
  - Canadian Pioneer Problems Project, 2.0 folders
  - Cance, Alexander E.
  - Carman, A B
  - Carpenter, Ford A.
  - Carter, Edward C
  - Carter, Floyd J.
  - Case, H C M
  - Catholic Economic Association
  - Chamberlain, James F.
  - Chapline, W R
  - Chase, Stuart, 1888
  - The Chevy Chase Bldg. and Loan Assoc.
  - Chilean Nitrate of Soda
  - Chinault
  - Clark, Noble
  - Clark University.
  - Coffman
  - Colby, Charles C
  - Colby College
  - Cole, Heath K
    See also: Continental Supply Company: Dellinger, David D., in:
  - Commercial National Bank
  - Commons, John R
  - The Continental Supply Company
  - Cooper, Homer
  - Cooper, Thomas
  - Co-operative Extension Work in Agriculture and Home Economics
  - Copeland
  - Cornell, A M
  - Cory, Ernest M
  - Cosby, Stanley W
  - Country Gentleman
  - The Country Home
  - Cox, S M
  - Crane, Jacob L Jr.
  - Crawford, D L
  - Creamer, Daniel B
  - Cressey, George B
  - Crew, Henry, 2.0 folders
  - Crisp
  - Cronin, Frank
  - Currie, John R
  - Dana, S T
  - Davis, Joseph S
    See: JEM - Binger, C A L
  - Delano, [Frederick?]
  - Dellinger, David D
  - Dellinger, Edwina H [Mrs. David D]
  - DeVault, S H
  - De Vries, Peter H
  - Dix, John E.
  - Doane, Robert R
  - Downs, L A
  - Doyle, Charles E., and Company.
  - Drinkard, A W, Jr.
  - Duddy, Mary Alice
  - Dunning, N Max
  - Earll, Donald M
  - East, Edward Murray, 1879-1938
  - Eastman, M Gale
  - Economic Geography
  - Ekblaw, W Elmer (Autograph)
  - Eke, Paul A
  - Elizabethtown College
  - Ellsworth, D W
  - Elvehjem, C A
    See also: JEM - Hart, E.B.; JEM - Rasmussen, in:
  - Ely, Richard T., 2.0 folders
  - Ely Economic Foundation, Inc.
  - Emminger, O
  - Englund, Eric E
  - Eppley, Geary
  - Erdman, H E
  - Estabrook, Leon M
  - Evering Poultry Farm and Hatchery
  - Fabila, Gilberto
  - Fairchild, Henry Pratt
  - Falconer, J I
  - The Farm Journal
  - Farquahar, Roger
  - Farrand, Livingston
  - The Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America
  - Federal Housing Administration
  - Federal Land Bank
  - Federal Life Insurance Company
  - Fenton, Mark
  - Fenzel, G
  - Field, Frederick V
  - Filley, H C
  - Finch, Vernon C
  - Firor, J William
  - Fleming, John R
  - Fogg, G W
  - Folsom, Josiah C
  - Ford, Alexander Hume
  - Foy, M F
  - Frame, Nat T
  - Frank, Glenn
  - French, Leslie
  - Frissell, Sydney
  - Fujimaki, Yukio
  - Gasson's Poultry Farms, Inc.
  - Gast, Ross H
  - Gaus, John M
  - Gee, Wilson
  - General Motors Corporation
  - Gilbert, Claude
  - Gilbert, George
    See: [Gilbert, Claude]
  - Glaeser, M C
  - Goode, J Paul
  - Goodman, R B
  - Gortner, Ross Aiken, 1885-1942
    See also: Publication Dept. - Rockefeller Institute, in:
  - Graham, Charles P
  - Gras, N S B
  - Gravatt, Annie R
  - Graves, H
    unlocated 6/2011
  - Graves, Lloyd M
  - Gray
  - Gray, L. C., 3.0 folders
    See also: Olsen, Nils A
  - Great Northern Railway Company
  - Greig, Agnes B
  - Grindley, T W
  - Grisdale, J H
  - Hamblin, Jack A
  - Hanks, Stanley C., Company.
  - Hannum, William Hamilton
  - Harper, Roland McMillian, 1878-1966
  - Harper and Brothers
  - Harriman, Henry I
  - Harrison, R
  - Harrison, Robert W
    See also: JEM - Baker, Z
  - Harrison, Shelby M
  - Hatch, K L
  - Hauter, L H
  - Hawkins, A H
  - Heaton, Herbert
  - Hedges, James B
  - Henderson, B
  - Hercules Powder Company
  - Hicks, W Mallan
  - Hildebrandt, Dorothee
  - Himebaugh, Keith
  - Hintz, Carl W
  - Ho, Franklin L
  - [Hobbard?], B H
  - Hochbaum, H W
  - Hoffman, Bertha E
  - Holman, Baker, Oliver Edwin.
  - Holmes, C L
  - Holt, Arthur E
  - Holt, Hamilton
  - Home Geographic Society
  - Hope, Clifford R
  - Hovgren, G E
  - Howard, T Levron
  - Huang, K C
  - Hudelson, Robert R
  - Hull, James D
  - Hume, Edward H
  - Hunger, Edwin A
  - Huntington, Ellsworth
  - Hurd, W Burton
  - Hutchinson, C B
  - Hutton, J G
  - Hyattsville Building Association
  - Hyde, Arthur M
  - Hyde, LeRoy W
  - Ideal Furnace Company
  - Illinois. Dept. of Insurance
  - Institute of Pacific Relations, 2.0 folders
  - Internal Revenue Service
  - Jardine, James T
  - Jensen, O B
  - Joel, A H
  - Joerg, W L G
  - Johnson, Charles S
    See also: Bryan, Helen R.; and, Fauset, C.R., in:
  - Johnson, Edw c
  - Johnson, F Webster
  - Johnson, Sherman
  - Jones, Clarence F
  - Jones, Edwin H, and Company
  - Jones, Ll Rodwell
  - Jordan, Virgil
  - Josephson, Clarence E
  - Journal of Land and Public Utility Economics
  - Julian, William Alexander
  - Jull, Morley A
  - Kalmanovitch
  - Kawai, Nobuzo
  - Keller, Albert D
  - Kellogg, Charles E
  - Kendall, Henry P
  - Kephart, L W
  - Kildee, H H
  - Kilpack, Gilbert H
  - King, Wilford I
  - Kline, J M, Jr.
  - Knopf, Alfred A
  - Kohler, Walter J
  - Kopman, I G
  - Kroncke, Sauthoff & Murphy
  - Kruse
  - LaGorce, John Oliver
  - Lattman, I
  - Laughlin, Harry Hamilton, 1880-
  - Lauterbach's Hillside Poultry Farm
  - Leader Farms
  - Lee, Hoon K
  - Lee, Shu-Ching
  - Letters of unknown identity
  - Levine, Rebecca
  - Li, Chang Wen
  - Lieu, D K
  - Ligutti, L G
  - Lindsay, Samuel D
  - Lipman, Jacob G
  - Lively, C E
  - The Living Age
  - Livingston, Burton Edward, 1875-1948
  - Lloyd, O G
  - Lobeck, Armin K
  - Loomis, Charles P
  - Lory, Charles A
  - Lowden, Frank Orren, 1861-1943
  - Lutheran Theological Seminary
  - Lynch, F C C
  - Lynch, Robert Newton
  - McArthur, D
  - McConnell, John P
  - McGee, Rosa
  - McGraw-Hill Book Company, Inc.
  - McGuire, C E
  - Mckelvie, Samuel R
  - McKnight, E J
  - McLachlen, Eugene H
  - McLachlen Banking Corporation
  - McLaren, W W
  - McNall, P E
  - McPhail
  - MacGibbon, D A
  - Mackintosh, William A
  - Madison [Wis.] Real Estate Board
  - Magruder, John W
  - Martin, Chester
  - Martin, Joseph W, Jr.
  - Maryland. Commissioner of Motor Vehicles
  - Maryland. Dept. of Insurance
  - Maryland. Dept. of Public Works
  - Maryland. Executive Dept.
  - Maryland. Montgomery County-Health Dept.
  - Maryland. Prince George's Co. Commissioners
  - Maryland. Prince George's Co. Police, Chief of
  - Maryland. Prince George's Co. Register of Wills
  - Maryland. Prince George's Co. Supervisor of Assessments
  - Maryland State Police
  - Mathushek Piano Manufacturing Company
  - Matsuda, Alfred Takeo
  - May, Stacy
  - Melvin, Bruce L
  - Meredith, Carey L
  - Merk, Frederick, 4.0 folders
  - Merom Institute
  - Merriam, Charles Edward, 1874-1953
  - Mertzke, Arthur J
  - Metropolitan Information Service
  - Metzger, J E
  - Meyer, George E
  - Milbank Memorial Fund
  - Miller, Cap E
  - Miller, Charles E
  - Miller, Charles Phillip, Jr.
  - Miller, J A
  - Mills, W H
  - Mitchell, Guy E
  - Mitchell, Wesley C
  - Moorhouse, L A
  - Morimoto, Kokichi
  - Moulton, Harold G
  - Mowatt, A
  - Mumford, Herbert Windsor, 1871-1902
  - Mutual Benefit Life Insurance Company
  - The Mutual Insurance Company
  - Myers, James
  - Myers, John Jacob
  - Narraway, A M
  - Nasu, Shiroshi
  - National Catholic Rural Life Conference
  - National Catholic Welfare Conference
  - National Cyclopedia of American Biography
  - National Geographic Society
  - National Life Insurance Company
  - National Mortgage and Investment Corporation
  - National Research Council
  - Neely, Wayne C
  - Nelson, O M
  - New Republic.
  - Newell, Jane Isabel
  - Nichols, W D
  - Notestein, Frank W
  - Nourse, E D
  - Odell, R K
  - O'Donnell, Paul J
  - Odum, Howard W
  - Ogburn, William Fielding, 1886-1959
  - O'Hara, Frank
  - O'Hara, Warren
  - Olmstead Brothers
  - Olsen, Nils A
  - Orcutt, John C
  - Oriental Culture Summer College of Tokyo
  - Orr, John
  - Ostrow, Alexander L
  - Otsuki, M
  - Oxford University Press
  - Park, Robert E
    See also: Singer, Isidor
  - Patterson, H J
  - Patterson, John K
  - Paxson, Chauncey G
  - Paxton
  - Pearl, Raymond, 1879-1940
    See also: Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine, in:
  - Penck, Albrecht
  - The Peoples Lumber and Supply Company
  - Perfection Stove Company
  - [Perleberg?], Curtinz L
  - Person, H S
  - Peters, F H
  - Peterson, Mabel J
  - Pillsbury Flour Mills Company
  - Pinchot, Gifford
  - Plummer, Clay
  - Plummer, Frank
  - Pollard, Arthur L
  - Potomac Archers
  - Potomac Electric Power Co.
  - Potter, Benjamin G
  - Power, Elmore
  - Powers, Ralph W
  - Preinkert, Miss
  - The Presbyterian Church in the U.S.: Executive Comm. of Religious Education and Publication
  - Proctor Academy
  - Provident Mutual Life Insurance Company of Philadelphia
  - Public Schools of the District of Columbia
  - Pugsley, C W
  - Pullman and Stevens, Inc.
  - Pyle, J. Freeman
  - Queen's Quarterly
  - The Rail
  - Ramsower, H C
  - Rand McNally & Company
  - Redpath Lyceum Bureau
  - Reed, O E
  - The Regional Planning Association of America
  - Resettlement Administration
  - Ridgely, Douglas C
  - Robb, Mrs.
  - Robert, Percy A
  - Rockford College
  - Rolfes
  - Roosevelt, Franklin Delano, pres.U.S., 1882-1945
    See also: National Academy of Sciences, 1941-1942, in:
  - Rose, Albert A
  - Rose, Helen B
  - Rose, W Gordon
  - Ross, E A
  - Rostovtzeff, Michael I
  - Roth, Walter E
  - Rozman, David
  - Rutherford, W. J., 3.0 folders
  - Rutledge, George and Sons, Ltd.
  - Rutledge, Ralph M
  - Ruzek, C V
  - Sanderson, Dwight
  - Satterlhwaite, A Y
  - Saucerman, Sophia
  - Sawtelle, Emily Hoag
  - The School of Living
  - Security Savings and Commercial Bank
  - Seedorf, W
  - Shelton, P H
  - Shiga, H
  - Shirk, Eli M
  - Shotwell, James T
  - Shutt, F T
  - Sibelka-Perleberg, Arthur J
  - The Sidwell Friends School
  - Sigma Xi
  - Simmerman, Emmett
  - Smith, E R P
  - Smith, Joseph Russell
  - Smith, J Stewart
  - Sneath-Baker Company, 3.0 folders
  - Sneath-Cunningham Company
  - Social Science Research Council; Committee on Problems and Policy
  - The Southern Planter
  - Spengler, Joseph J
  - Sproul, Robert E
  - Stark, Paul E., Company.
  - Stewart, Charles L
  - Stewart, P H
  - Stine, O C
  - Su, Lee
  - The Suburban District Building Association
  - The Survey - Survey Graphic Survey Associates, Inc.
  - Symons, T B
  - Taber, Louis J
  - Tanahashi, H
  - Taylor, Carl C., 2.0 folders
  - Taylor, E H
  - Taylor, Griffith
  - Taylor, William A
  - Taylor-Hibbard Club
  - Teleky, Paul
  - Tennessee Valley Authority
  - Tenny
  - Terpenning, Walter A
  - Thomas, R P
  - Thomas, W Preston
  - Tillett, B D
  - Tobata, Seiichi
  - Tory, H M
  - Toteff, A U
  - Troyer, Robert M
  - Tulaikov, N
  - Turner, Mrs.
  - Tyler, McMahon, Smith & Wilson
  - The Union Deposit Company
  - United Press Associations
  - U S Civil Service Commission
  - U. S. Department of Agriculture.
  - United States. Department of the Interior.
  - U.S. Office of Price Administration
  - U.S. Treasury Department.
  - University of Pennsylvania Press
  - Vance, Rubert B
  - The Vandermast Farm
  - Vaughan, Thomas Wayland, 1870-1952
    See also: National Academy of Medicine - John J. Carty Medal, in:
  - Virginia, Commonwealth of
  - Visher, Stephen S
    See: Bowman, Isaiah
  - Voorhies, Edwin C
  - Wallace, Henry Agard, 1888-1965
  - Wallace, L W
  - [Walleus?], L
  - Wantrup, Siegfried von Ciriacy
  - Warburton, C W
  - Warren, G F
  - Waterman, Alma M
  - Webster, Wilfred
  - Weeks, David
  - Wehrwein, George S
  - Weller, John D
  - Welsh, T H
  - Westervelt, W I
  - Wheldon & Wesley, Ltd.
  - White, David
    See also: National Academy of Sciences, in:
  - Whitson, A R
  - Wicks, Stanton D
  - Wilbur, Ray Lyman
  - Wilcox, E V
  - Wilcox Air Conditioning Corporation
  - Willard, Rex E
  - Willits, Joseph H
  - Wilson, Edmund Beecher, 1856-1939
  - Wilson, E Raymond
  - Wilson, George G
  - Wilson, M L
  - Wissler, Clark
  - Wittfogel, Karl August
  - Wood, G Burton
  - Woodward and Lothrop
  - Worrell, Miss B
  - Wright, Quincy
  - Wrigley, Gladys M
  - Wyatt, F A
  - Yale Alumni Association
  - Yamasaki, Mituko
  - Young, Donald R
  - Young, Owen D
  - Ziegler, Jesse H
  - Zimmer, David B
  - Zorner, H